All right.
She'll be back. Good evening everyone.
I played musical chairs this evening. I
will be your host for tonight's finance
meeting and the regular meeting when we
get to that. So, calling the finance
meeting for November 17th to order.
We're going to get right into new
resolutions starting with temporary
resolution 9625. That's coming through
water water pollution control. That's
Mr. Wing.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. chairman. Uh, this
resolution authorizes the SSD to enter
contracts with Ferdantis to utilize
their inspection engineering services um
for the water water pollution and storm
water departments when they're working
on infrastructure projects. Um, I'd like
to invite uh Stephen to give some more
background on this, but uh I do believe
this is an annual piece that we usually
pass.
>> Thank you, Councilman. Good evening,
everybody. Uh, yes, as noted, this
contract we sign is an annual contract.
We've been doing it for years now with
uh the engineering consultant firm
Verdantis. Uh they provide us again um
engineering services on small projects.
Uh and primarily inspection is what we
typically most of the contracts use for
inspections. Hard to find good
inspectors and we have several with
them. Um and have had good success with
them. So uh again we utilize them for
that purpose for the most part. Um again
I don't know there's much else to add
but I'm happy to answer any questions if
anybody's not clear about anything. Any
questions?
No, Mr. Wayne.
>> Yep. Uh, Council Tina will be my second
and um we can go a full three readings
on this.
>> Okay.
>> I had two. So, you want to do three?
>> Three works fine for me. Sorry.
>> No,
>> two.
>> Okay. So I respond to
>> I apologize. Sorry. Okay. Um so at the
law director administration meeting on
Wednesday um the mayor advised that
President Porter wanted to um shrink the
number of meetings so that the December
15th meeting could be used for
potentially swearing in the new members.
Um and so they had asked me to um
truncate basically the number of
readings so that there wouldn't have to
be a full council uh a full finance and
council meeting prior to swearing in all
of the new members. So I apologize. I
made that too. Um Stephen did indicate
three on his request, but I did that
after speaking with the mayor and and at
President Porter's request. So
>> Okay.
>> Thanks.
>> Okay. So I I'll move to suspend next
meeting.
>> Okay.
Thank you. Temporary resolution 9725
that's coming through law committee.
Mrs. Crates.
>> Yes, thank you. Um, this will allow the
city to join a multi-dist litigation
against 3M, DuPont, and other
defendants. The city was notified as a
potential pliff in 2023, but because of
testing and limited testing providers
available, the city was just able to
determine its qualification as a plif in
October of this year. The deadline to
apply for settlement funds is January
1st of 2026. But because of the process
involved, it's cumbersome. It takes time
and there's a lot of data that needs to
be entered. We're going to ask for
suspension because it can't be completed
beyond the initial info page until
council approves. I do want to note that
the associated fees for plaintiffs
council comes out of settlement funds
and therefore the city has no additional
cost beyond the testing to determine if
we qualify as plaintiffs. Law director
Hall, is there anything additional you'd
like to add to that?
>> No, ma'am. Thank you.
and Mr. Bisch will be my second.
>> Any questions from anyone?
Seeing none, we'll move to temporary
resolution 9825 through administrative
services. Mr. Luxembourg.
>> Hey, is this just uh
this is just uh a new contract
uh with Renaissance Counseling and
Consultation
uh to continue providing mental health
uh counseling services to Lancaster
employees. And this is a three-year
um contract and we'll be going for two
readings.
>> Great. Mr. M. Jackson, I have is your
second. Anybody have any questions?
Anything you'd like to add, Miss Woody?
>> I mean, not necessarily. I think that
Mr. Luckenberg summed that up nicely.
>> I thought I did, too. But you were
eyeballing. I was waiting for your hand
cuz last time I missed your hand.
>> I'm just used to Mr. Luckenberg calling
on me, so I was all ready to go.
>> I like this view better because I missed
your hand last time and I thought she's
going to raise her hand and I'm going to
be in trouble. So,
>> but I'm happy to answer any other
questions.
>> No, it's well explained. Anybody else?
No. All right. Temporary resolution 9925
that's coming through economic
development. Mrs. Hoop.
>> Yes. Thank you. Um we have annexed three
different areas. Um Euing Woods, Victory
Commons, and Fairfield Park. Um and so
we need to add them to the housing
survey to include them in the city CRA.
So that's what this and then um if I
could direct
the rest to law director Hall. Um,
regarding the suspension.
>> Yes, ma'am. So, uh,
one of these properties, the Sheridan
Drive property, which is Euing Woods,
will have both a CRA and a TIFF on it.
And because a CRA takes precedence over
a TIFF, we need to get the CRA put in
place first. The TIFF will come next
meeting. So, we want the CRA in place
before the TIFF happens because that CRA
abatement needs to take precedence. if
that makes sense. And if anybody has any
questions, I'm more than happy to answer
those.
>> I see none. Miss
>> um Mrs. Crates. And again, we're going
to suspend
today.
>> Mr. Crates is your second.
>> Second. Yeah.
>> Okay.
All right. Uh temporary resolution
100-25
coming through public works. Miss Tener.
>> Yes. I'm going to have her come up and
speak about this. This is regarding the
pedestrian project for Memorial Pierce.
We need to get a grant in by the 30th of
November.
We just need to suspend tonight.
>> Good evening. Um
this is a a grant that we became aware
of and recently ODOT has um encouraged
us to apply for it. It's called a
transportation alternative program. a
tap grant. It's an 8020
match for the Memorial Drive Pierce
Avenue sidewalk project that we received
a corpo grant to do the engineering
that's finished. just recently received
another grant to do the rightway
acquisition that will start soon
u and will be finished we think in about
a year and if we go after this grant and
get this grant then we'll be able to
roll right into construction of those
improvements. Um which is why I didn't
want to wait until next November to
submit it. Uh because the timing
wouldn't have worked out as well. Uh
it's due on November 30th. Um, so I need
to get it approved at this meeting. So I
appreciate
>> And our our match is 20%. Correct.
>> 20%.
>> Yeah. And we'll get that. We have some
of the multi-trail discretionary
funding. Um, we're going to look into
that as as a potential match. Hopefully
there's enough there that we can bank it
up.
>> Any questions about the project or the
grant?
Don't see any. Miss Tiner
>> and Mr. Luckenberg will be my second.
Okay.
>> Thank you, Kurt.
>> Thanks, Kurt.
>> All right. Do we have any other new
resolutions?
>> We'll talk about the budget in a little
bit here. All right. New ordinances. We
just have one temporary ordinance 7025
coming through economic development. Mr.
too.
>> Yes. Thank you. Um I think Stephanie
Okay, good. Stephanie's here. I didn't
see her. Um just quickly, there's a
property on Broad Street that um is
doing PACE PACE financing and that
requires the city to join the EIED. So,
>> so the 7025 is the new tiff for the
residential viewing. But I am going to
talk about the east. So you on the right
track.
>> Yes. So this is just the residential
portion of the tiff for the Sheridan
property. So when we say residential,
it's for the the single family homes.
Remember how they call the multi- they
call that uh commercial and we've
already started that. Is that one
totally done? Isn't that totally done?
Okay, good. Um this is why I I have my
attorney here. Um but uh this is for the
residential side. It's for the single
family homes because you know it's
broken up into two different types of
tiffs. So
it's for Sheridan.
>> Any questions?
>> No.
>> And we're doing the two readings. Yeah.
Two readings.
>> Two readings. Wing's going to be my
second or my Yeah. second.
>> All right.
That feels like a blistering pace that
we just set. So, it's going to come to a
screeching halt here pretty soon. But in
the meantime, thank you. And we're going
to move on to department updates. So,
anybody here with a department update?
So, um, one thing that was in my email
this last week is that there is a PACE
project for the Wilson building just
down the street on Broad in order. So, a
PACE project is making improvements,
energy um, efficiency improvements. So,
in this case, uh, rooftop uh, roof um,
and windows and LED lighting. So, PACE
program does upfront financing for the
owner of the property and then they pay
it back with a special assessment on
their property taxes. Well, in order for
the Wilson building owners to do a PACE
project, we the city of Lancaster has to
be added to the EID energy special
improvement district. So, you guys have
heard of SIDS because of DDL's SID for
downtown. This is an energy SID. It's um
so the EID is the program administrator
and it is a public entity governed by a
board and because they are the
administrator of PACE we just have to
join that association and once uh once
Lancaster is in the EID it actually
opens the door for any PACE project that
that uh owners in Lancaster want to
participate in. So, it's actually a
one-time action that has long-term
positive effects. So, um um just
checking my notes. I think that's pretty
much all I wanted to say. So, we don't
have to pay a fee to join Eid. It's just
something that we have to vote on. And
then again, like I said, then we're in
the EID and it opens up the door for any
land owner or property owner to do pace
improvements on their property.
A little wordy. I'm sorry.
And I'm I'm you know if you want to ask
any questions I'm happy to answer them.
So we'll see that next time.
>> Okay. Any questions for Miss Bosco?
>> Seeing none. Thank you for your update.
>> Good evening members of council. Um I
have three brief updates for the fire
department tonight. Um the first the
auxiliary building construction is
nearly complete. um the building that's
um putting behind engine house 3 um
would note that during the construction
process we found that the water service
and the gas service to the existing
firehouse were also in need of repair.
So while the construction was ongoing we
went ahead and replaced those. Um also
like to thank the gas department for all
their help running the new gas line to
the firehouse and to our new building.
Uh secondly, the medic that we acquired
um here recently is now in service uh
serving the citizens of Langster out of
engine house number one. And finally,
I'm proud to announce that as of this
morning, the Langster Fire Department is
fully fully staffed at our authorized
force of 84 firefighters.
I appreciate all the the support and the
patience of council and the city
administration and helping us reach that
milestone.
Thank you.
Good evening. I just wanted to take a
quick minute to thank everyone for your
continued support for our CDBG programs.
Um, I'm going to read an appreciation
email that was sent to the mayor a
couple weeks ago, but I thought it was
important to hear, you know, some
feedback on the good that our programs
are doing. Hello. I'm writing to share
the story of having our house improved
through the city of Lancaster. My
husband and I bought a house on
Washington Avenue in 2002. It's an old
house from the 1800s. Needless to say,
there were numerous issues that we
needed to help with. We didn't make
enough money to tackle everything, so we
did what we could, such as putting
plastic around the windows every winter.
Even with plastic, we could see movement
from the curtains and felt cold air
coming in there, as well as our old
doors. I heard about the community
development through a neighborhood and
signed up to get on the waiting list.
When we received the phone call that
they were ready to begin the process, we
were thrilled. I took before and after
pictures to show the progress. My
husband retired a few years ago, so his
income was reduced a lot. When the city
of Lancaster sent a company this past
summer, it happened at the perfect time.
They were so professional and worked
quickly and efficiently. We have new
floors upstairs and the steps. We have
siding now. We have new windows and two
new doors. Our outside paint on the
house was peeling bad and my husband was
no longer able to paint it again. Also,
it was found that we had lead paint
around the windows. All of that was
safely removed and they painted around
the windows. They even replaced our old
front porch and it's so pretty. I know
it does improve the look of our
neighborhood. So, it really benefits
more people than us. I'm unsure if other
lowincome house owners even are aware of
this wonderful program. They should know
this has been a huge blessing for us.
And they are coming next week to gut our
ancient bathroom and put a walk-in
shower with a shower chair, new sink and
toilet, as well as flooring. It's so
appreciated by my husband and I. I
wanted to let you know how incredibly
important this assistance is for the
citizens of Lancaster. I've lived in
this community my entire life. I'm 62
and my husband Jack is 68. We're looking
forward to a warmer house this winter.
So, I just wanted to give you kind of a
a little update on how important this is
for our community.
>> Thank you.
Anyone else for department updates?
>> I
general fund money. I'm going to go with
yes.
>> I'm not in a department. I am an office.
Yes. Bob Wolfinger always thought I was
a department head. So, uh, I just came
because I think you're voting on the
budget tonight and I'm part of your
budget and I feel obligated to come see
you since you fund me. So, I'm here if
you have any questions about what my
budget is. Um, and the fact that I do
appreciate the support that you do give
us in the court. Uh, and again, we try
to do as much as we can with alternative
sources uh, to keep your costs down. Uh,
I think out of our special projects
funds this year, we will have spent
$841,000.
Uh, which is kind of strange for a court
to generate that kind of money, but that
pays off the I think the bond. I'm
looking at Jackie because she knows all
this. The bond, the second what I call
the second mortgage, uh, heating and
cooling and the electric bill. So, also,
we still have grants that are running.
Uh, my Veterans Court grant doesn't
expire until 27. That's over 900,000.
Now, we'll see where that goes given the
fact that certain things have kind of
been frozen. My drug court gets over
$750,000 over a three-year period. Uh it
will expire September of next year, but
our new grants writer is hard at work
and we do get money from the state for
all veterans, drug and or mental health
and drug court. So, we do try to
alleviate some of the cost to the city
uh so that you're not funding us at
those levels. But if you have any
questions, that's why I come. I for 10
years I feel obligated. You know, you
you fund me. You should have the right
to take a shot at me if you want.
>> So go ahead.
>> But if you don't, I'm good. Thank you.
>> Anybody want to take a shot at Judge
Fields before he
>> not really sure I advise that? We have
no choice. We have to
>> We don't have any choice. We have to
>> That's what I tell defendants when
they're going to ask you. We have no
choice.
>> Broad shoulders. I'm used to it. So
>> all right. Thank you.
>> You're welcome. Thank you.
Any other department updates?
All right. Seeing none, I'm going to
move into
meeting prep for tonight's council
meeting. We do have two public hearings
um that will do before reading of
resolutions. That is on the short-term
rental legislation we have and the Arbor
Homes. Um that is shared. No, that is
Rainbow Drive. You fixed that. Uh on
Rainbow Drive, it's potential zoning map
amendment. So, we'll have those two and
then I wrote it down. I don't know that
I spelled it correctly, but so just so
everyone's on the same page. So, we have
the new starred version of the budget.
We're not going to be voting on the
budget tonight. So everybody has another
two weeks to digest. So that means the
third reading of all of the pay
ordinances. I'm going to request to have
those tabled. So we're just going to
table those. So then when we go to deal
with the budget next meeting, we will
take those off the table and vote on
those as well. Just so everyone is aware
and on the same page. Everybody that
makes sense to everyone.
Great.
Um, and then that's all I have for the
regular meeting and then we're going to
move to other discussion items. Do we
have anything before we want to discuss
the star version of the budget?
>> If you don't mind, maybe I go ahead and
give my remarks on the budget and then
questions come up.
>> Yep.
>> So, in front of you, you have the
starred version of the 2026
city budget.
should note that it's a $229 million
budget.
Last year was $ 297 million. Uh most of
that is uh enterprise departments uh
things that you'll see in the budget. So
first of all, I want to thank Director
Woody, department heads, Auditor
Nettles, Anitra, Treasure Stoen, and all
the council members who I've spoken to
over the last couple months during the
budgeting process. Uh it's been really
helpful. Council
committees, thank you for reviewing your
budgets with your department heads and
asking questions and uh moving a lot of
those things forward. A lot of that is
incorporated in the budget. You see,
uh it should be noted that we've
reviewed every line in the budget
multiple times and your changes are
reflected in red or black depending
mostly red which mean decreases.
Uh we've seen significant decreases in
general fund budgeting.
um millions of dollars.
Um some things that impacted our budget
uh and you'll see wages
as you know we have five
uh bargaining units in the city uh
police fire complex uh as me and police
supervisors.
They each one of those unions uh
negotiated with the city and received
three-year contracts that started um
this will be the fi uh next year will be
the final year. So we'll be negotiating
with all five unions next year for their
salary and benefits.
Uh police fire complex received a 5% pay
increase for 2026.
Aspir received a 4% pay increase for
2026. These are contracts that were
agreed upon three years ago. U
management non-union is set by
administration and we set that for 2026
at 2.5%.
We talked about 26 versus 27 pays. What
does that mean to the city? What it
means is $1.7 million in the 2026
budget. So when you hear about that, it
is not insignificant to have a 27th pay.
All union members are hourly employees.
They get paid for every hour they work.
So they don't work for free in the 27th
pay. Uh it should be noted that elected
officials are different than that. We
have a set salary for elected officials.
It doesn't matter if it's 27 pays or 26
pays. It's the same annual salary for
elected officials.
So that's just something for your memory
and to to understand. It's a little
different for hourly employees. We have
a 3% increase in health insurance cost
which is well below the what the market
is seeing in central Ohio.
Uh our enterprise funds and our
department heads were tasked with
balancing their budget so that they have
revenue to support their expenses and I
will say that all of them were able to
do so.
Uh last year uh in the general fund
we utilized
additional funding in the 2046 account
which is our 0.15 fire levy. Our 2047
account which is our point our first
point45 police and fire levy and our 201
account which is our 045 the most recent
uh safety levy that was passed.
that allowed us to save money in the
general fund, but once you take that
carryover and you spend it, it's like a
savings account. It's gone. So that that
carryover in all three of those funds is
reduced back to a level uh sufficient
for the auditor to have carryover for
the first quarter of 2026, but not a
substantial savings account for the
future.
So we balanced our police and fire
budget from the general fund and that's
the original 0.1 or one 1% that was uh
council imposed income taxes.
So even that carryover is reduced by the
spending that we're doing in in the
general fund
and you will see that reflected in in
the budget.
So some other things that we need to
think about as we go forward. Um we have
taken steps on the administration side
to limit um purchase of vehicles uh
replacing uh general fund positions uh
and enterprise positions that um that we
may be able to avoid replacing because
we have someone else that can do the
work. We've done that as you've seen in
utilities and some of the other
departments. we've been able to do some
uh reorganization
and elimination of some positions that
were duplicating services and or we
could provide better service in planning
and zoning versus a third supervisor in
utilities. So you saw the downsizing
there. We will continue to do those
things going forward
as 26 unfolds. Um
we may need to come to council. This is
a zerobased budget.
If you don't know what that means, old
city budgeting was done when I first got
on where you just threw 10% or 5% on to
what you did last year and you continue
to build that forever.
This budget's based on what it cost
and how much we have and it's budgeted
to that dollar amount. So, it's it's if
we have 84 firefighters, for instance,
we know what they cost. It's zerobased.
We're not throwing 10% on above that.
We're budgeting for our staffing and for
our needs. If we need a $400,000 medic,
it would be budgeted for for 400,000,
not 430,000, etc., etc. So, it is to the
best of our ability, it's zerobased
budgeting.
What that means though is if something
comes up where we need something in
addition that's not in this budget
because we don't have a wish list item
in the budget, we might have to come
back to council and ask for funding. But
we're only going to do that, and this is
my assurance to you, is if we know that
we need it and can support it and the
funding is available.
A couple of things should be on your
radar. It should be on everyone's radar
in the state. The House, the Ohio House
has a couple of bills pending in front
of them that can impact and probably
will impact the city of Lanster in a
very negative way. House Bill 503, the
Ways and Means Committee, is looking at
how
communities provide commuter tax credit
for people who pay income tax in
multiple cities. They work in Columbus.
They live in Lancaster. They're looking
at
reconsidering how that is done on the
credit side. Right now, we provide a
full 1% credit uh to people who work
outside the city but live here. Uh that
that is the the again council imposed
many years ago 1% income tax on the
citizens. It was not voted upon. It was
voted on c by council only but not by
the citizens. Every other income tax
that we currently have in place, the
three I mentioned uh earlier, the 0.15,
the 2.45, were all voted on by our
taxpayers
to provide services that we provide to
the community. Whatever that service may
be, including our 3 mil property tax
level levy was voted on by the community
to provide better streets and alleys and
curbing and sidewalk, etc.
The state has decided, the state house
has decided to get into some of those
things uh that may dramatically impact
us. If House Bill 503 would pass and it
would take away that 1% credit, well,
actually, what it would is give full
credit for the full income tax. So,
instead of having a 1% credit, someone
might have a 2.3% credit. That means
they pay zero to the city they live in.
>> That's crazy. But they pay everything to
whatever Columbus wants. 2.5% up there,
I believe. Um, I have authored a
opposition letter and sent it to the
state in hopes that it might be
considered as opponent testimony. Uh, I
know other communities have done that
along with the Ohio Municipal League and
the Ohio Mayor's Alliance. And I've been
told that they have taken notice of the
opponent testimony and they it has
slowed down. That doesn't mean it's
stopped. it's slowed down. Let's hope
it's stopped. Uh the state should worry
about the state and Lancaster worry
about Lancaster, but that's, you know,
we'll have to fight that battle and
currently we're fighting that battle.
The other thing,
currently police officers, uh we pay
19.5%
into the Ohio Police and Fire pension
for police officers. We pay 24%, this is
of their salaries for firefighters.
That's different because it's been
historically different going back 30
years.
There is a movement to make it even at
24%. Of course, they're not going to
bring it down to 19 and a half% for
everybody. They're going to make it 24%
for everybody. For us, that's $400,000.
That's equal to about three police
officers salary and benefits.
I anticipate that's going to pass and it
will impact every community in the state
of Ohio.
Um and there's other things uh you
certainly know about the the citizen
referendum on property tax abolishment.
Um certainly property tax reform I think
is a necessary thing. I think there
needs to be some consideration for uh
homesteading etc etc. But uh the real
dollar impact for us if House Bill 503
would pass and a full credit was
provided for people working outside the
city and property tax abolishment it
would happen
and throw in the police and fire
pension. We're talking probably $9
million from the general fund.
We can't absorb
$9 million loss in general fund.
So, this should be on your radar. If you
want to send a letter to the state and
tell them how you feel about some of
these things, please feel free to do so.
But these things are things that we
can't ignore. We have to be aware of.
They have to be on our radar. We have to
be thinking about them. We have to think
about how they're going to impact us and
our community going forward.
Reminder, our community voted
for services they wanted.
Uh, three years ago, we voted to add
additional police and firefighters and
additional medic and and move our safety
forces forward. We voted for a 3M levy
to prepare our streets and keep things
moving forward. The state,
at least on a couple of these things,
the state state house has decided they
want to weigh in on it and certainly our
citizens in our state have a right to
weigh in on on things also. So, we're
going to probably be impacted
significantly at some point and then
we'll have to respond at some point.
Those things are all considered in your
budget that you have in front of you.
That's why you've seen reductions in
areas that you might think, why did we
do that? I'm I'm preparing us for the
future. And I think everybody I've
spoken to, auditor, treasurer, uh
council people, uh we've talked about
these things and I I think we all need
to be really fully aware of how the
state house can impact Lancaster, Ohio.
So there's my budget discussion. Thank
you.
>> Thank you.
Anybody have any questions on the
starred version that we have in front of
us? Miss Tiner,
>> I do have a question. So, we they um
have 84 firefighters. Are we still going
to have 79 police officers? Because that
was the
>> we have 84 firefighters because we have
84 firefighters today. Uh we're
we're not going to be hiring any more
additional general fund positions and
police and and or fire until we can find
out how our finances are going to look
going forward. I think it's unwise to
continue to add people to the city uh
payroll uh in 2026 without a full
understanding of the impact.
>> Okay. Okay. Well, the thing is I knew
that with uh court we have to take two
officers and put them over at the
courthouse. So, that's going to take two
off the street right there.
>> Yeah. They cost us about $142,000 a
piece.
>> So, they
>> Well, we need to consider I don't know.
I I won't be on, but when they do the
next union thing, I mean, all the fire
departments have two men medics that
even Columbus does, and we have three.
So that might be something that needs to
be considered.
>> We will be looking at all those things.
Um during the budgeting process, we were
able to see things that that that really
became apparent um over the last several
weeks. Um those of you recall when we
passed the 045 uh the administration at
the time uh sat and discussed how many
firefighters it should be added, how
many police officers should be added and
and they provided these numbers to us
8479.
We inherited those numbers. However,
inherited or not, it is not wise
to outpace your funding. And I'm
seriously concerned about overspending
to the point where 5 years from now,
where are we at?
I'm not going to be seeking during my
time as mayor additional income taxes. I
won't be asking for them. We're going to
live within our means and we're going to
make it work. I feel the same about rate
increases. We just did rate increases.
We're not going to be increasing rates
again to add people. We are going to
maintain our services. We're going to do
what we promised to do, but we're we're
not going to outspend our revenue. And
um and I think knowing everybody here, I
think you would agree with me.
These are tough conversations, not
pleasant conversations, but we have to
have them. We have to be realistic about
what the state's throwing at us and what
our job is here. and we've been given a
dollar amount of income that we have. We
have to live within our means.
So, it will be some belt tightening.
Thank you. Any other questions?
So, again, we'll have the two weeks in
between this meeting and the next for
you guys to come up with any questions.
This will stay on the table. We'll
replace it. Well, it'll come off the
table next meeting. We'll replace it
with this version as long as there
aren't any other changes. And then same
with the pay ordinances, we'll look to
vote on those next meeting.
Okay. Any
other topics for discussion?
Seeing none, I will ask for a motion to
adjurnn.
>> So moved.
>> Second. And we are adjourned at 6:35 and
the regular council meeting will start
at 6:45.
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 74-653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our two
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
Hi, I'm Corey Clark with Fairfield
County Job and Family Services. Our
mission is to protect children and
elderly, encourage family stability, and
promote self-reliance for a stronger
community. We're honored to be selected
by the Buckeye family's Buckeye Cares
program. That means Buckeye will make a
donation with each vehicle sold this
month. From all of us at Fairfield
County Job and Family Services, thanks
Buckeye for your ongoing support for
local families.
I appreciate everyone staying up. We're
going to we're throwing a a kink in
this. So, we have a new council member
that's joining us this evening and we
need to swear him in before
we start this meeting.
>> I think you can let them all sit down.
>> Yeah, please. Please feel free to sit
unless I mean we definitely want to ar
>> we were putting the pressure on right
off the rip. The whole room was
standing.
>> Usually somebody holds the
>> Yeah. So that I have a hand
>> front and center.
You can stand right here so everybody
can see you.
>> You want to place your left hand, raise
your right hand, and repeat after me. I,
John Carr, Jr. do solemnly swear
>> I, John Jr., to solemnly swear
>> that I will support the Constitution of
the United States
>> the Constitution of the State of Ohio
>> and the ordinances of the city of
Lancaster, Ohio.
>> The ordinance of the city of Lancaster,
Ohio.
>> And that I will faithfully
>> and I will faithfully,
>> honestly, and impartially
>> honestly and impartially
>> discharge the duties of the office
>> of city council
>> as an atlarge representative
>> for the city of Lancaster, Ohio
>> for the city of Lancaster, Ohio. during
the term which runs
>> during the term which runs
>> January 1st, 2024
>> through December 31st, 2025
>> through December 31st, 2025.
>> Awesome. Congratulations.
All right. Before we start the meeting
officially with a pledge of allegiance.
So, President Porter usually gives the
same little I don't have a prayer, but
um you
>> have a prayer.
>> Yes or no? Should I sit down? I don't
know.
>> You're making me nervous.
>> I was making you nervous.
>> It's It's the holiday season. So, I've
talked about it before. I bring it up
all the time wherever I'm talking to
someone, but the art of neighboring,
right? So, there's multiple principles.
I won't go all o over all of them, but
the practice reciprocal
reciprocal hospitality.
So,
Be nice to your neighbor. Pay attention
to your neighbor. Help your neighbor.
Maybe you need some help and your
neighbor's willing to help you. We I I
don't want to make this political, but
we can reach out and touch you faster
than anybody else can. Doesn't matter,
you know, the decisions that we make
here, the decisions that you make at
home, whether you put up a a really
weird fence cuz you don't like the
neighbor's dog or whatever the case may
be. um just it's that time of year to
give thanks and be thankful to to what
we have and maybe help someone that's
not as fortunate. So that's where I'm
going to jump off my soap box except to
say please spay and neuter your pets.
All right. Call this meeting to order.
We'll start with the pledge of
allegiance
to the flag of the United States of
America and to the republic for which it
stands. One nation under God,
indivisible, with liberty and justice
for all.
I ask the clerk to please call the role.
>> Mr. Als
>> here.
>> Mr. Pisch here.
>> Mr. Carr
>> here.
>> Mrs. Kates
>> Mrs. Hoop
>> here. Mr. Luenberg
>> here.
>> Mr. Scoover
>> Mr. Sully
>> here.
>> Miss Ter here. And Mr. Wing
Uh, can I get a motion to excuse
President Porter, please?
>> I make a motion. Excuse President
Porter.
>> Second.
>> Mr. Porter is excused.
Reading and disposal of the journal.
>> I have regular meeting minutes dated
November 3rd, 2025.
>> Mr. President, I would like to make a
motion to accept the reading and
disposing of the journal.
>> Second.
We have a motion and a second to dispose
of the journal. Uh all those in favor
signify signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All oppose. Same sign. Motion carries.
Do we have any reports of city
officials?
>> I do have four. I have email dated
November 4th, 2025 for zoning
verification
letter request submitted by the city
planner Chasyn Carter. Email data
November 5th, 2025 regarding census
contract for gas smart meter initiative
um permanent ordinance 54-25 submitted
by law director Stephanie Hall. Email
dated November 12th, 2025 regarding
October 2025 income tax collection
report submitted by tax commissioner Amy
Hamilton. Email dated November 13, 2025
regarding city hall restoration window
replacement submitted by service safety
director Carrie Woody.
>> Mr. President, I make a motion to accept
the reports of city officials.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion, a second to accept and
file the reports of city officials. All
in favor signify by saying I.
>> I. All post, same sign. Motion carries.
>> Do we have any communications?
>> I do. I have four of them. I have email
dated November 5th, 2025 regarding
public hearing on parcel 053141-625000
submitted by Jeff and Cheryl Jones
homeowners um mail dated November 13,
2025 regarding liquor license requests
submitted by Department of Commercial
Commerce um Division of Liquor Control.
series of emails dated November 4th
through the 17th, 2025 regarding public
records requests submitted by a Grant
Pototts research specialist. And
finally, an email dated November 17,
2025 regarding reszoning Arbor home
of Arbor Homes um submitted by Jimmy and
Sarah Bird homeowners.
>> Mr. President, I make a motion to accept
communications.
>> Second. We have a motion and a second to
accept father communications. All in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
>> All oppose, same sign. Motion carries.
Do we have any special presentations or
awards?
>> I have none this evening.
>> Any petitions or memorials?
>> No petition or memorials.
>> All right.
All right. Now is the time we set aside
for voters and taxpayers to address
council. Are there any citizens who'd
like to speak directly to council
regarding any subject tonight other than
the two public hearings? We will open up
in a minute. Mr. James.
Thank you. Good evening, esteemed
members of council and city officials.
My name is Tom James. I reside at the
352 Mound Street here in our great city.
I'd like to start tonight by saying on
October 1st of this year, I had the
privilege of attending the grand opening
of our new state-of-the-art water
treatment facility on Memorial Drive and
6th Avenue to meet the growing demand
for water and the need to replace an
aging treatment facility. This facility
was designed in a very short period of
time and was completed on schedule. I
want to personally thank members of this
legisl legislative body, city
administration, and many of the tireless
efforts of our engineering and water
department staff for making this happen.
Without minimizing the efforts of so
many who helped complete this project,
I'd like to re recognize the efforts of
two persons who lived with this project
from day one. Denise Cruz and Steven
Welstead not only were key to helping
complete this project, but they did so
while still handling all of their other
job duties. Their contribution was and
is indeed remarkable.
Some of you realize what was just
accomplished here with bringing this
project to a successful conclusion. But
many of you do not realize that this was
accomplished with very low interest
rates because you don't add this kind of
important addition to our ca our
infrastructure without with cash on
hand. You do it with good financial
standing of our city and over the years
has been carefully and judiciously
managed.
Due to the fact that the planning
initial con design of this treatment
facility was completed on an accelerated
schedule, I'm not at all surprised that
some changes were required during the
construction phase which obviously
resulted in additional costs. In the
final analysis, the investment we've
made in this capital project is truly a
bargain. To construct this same uh
facility in five years or even one year
from now, in my opinion, will be
significantly more expensive. We now
have the capacity to respond to the
growth of our city very far into the
future. Now, aside from some of the
comments about the new water treatment
plant, I'd like to address some of the
current and future members of our city
council. Soon, many of you will be
leaving this leaving your positions.
Your expertise, experience, and
dedication will certainly be missed.
Your dedicated service is certainly
admirable. To the new members soon to
join this council, my hope, prayer, and
my expectation as a concerned citizen
that you accept this responsibility
without preconceived notions, hidden
agendas, and that you do your homework
before you're sworn in. If you have not
already done so, spend time with our
city treasurer, our mayor, and all and
some of the uh department heads to gain
a working knowledge of the budget
process and appreciation for what it
takes for a city of our size to effect
effectively function. The budget is a
whole lot more than just line items on a
spreadsheet. Because unless you have
personally been tasked with developing a
detailed budget in your work life, then
you have no appreciation for the massive
effort that goes through into
forecasting what your future and
potential expenses revenues will be.
Once council approves that budget, that
department head is now accountable for
that entire budget.
>> I am certainly been proud to have been a
former member of this legislative body
and a member of the standing committee
that helped launch the water treatment
plant project. I'm also grateful for
having had the opportunity to work with
so many competent and caring people
within the ranks of our city and with
many of you on this council.
>> Everyone that I had the pleasure
>> your three minutes are up, man. I gave
you more than that. Sorry.
>> You'll just have to read the rest in
paper. Okay.
>> Yeah. Appreciate it though. Thank you.
>> Anybody else want to address? I forgot
to mention the threeminute part, but I
knew you already knew that. So, all
right. Anybody
else want to address council?
All right. Again, thank you, Mr. James.
Okay. Uh, reports of standing
committees, please.
>> I have six of them. I have law committee
agenda meeting agenda dated November
4th, 2025 submitted by Mrs. Kes.
Economic development committee meeting
minutes dated November 4th, 2025
submitted by Mrs. Hoop. Public Works
Committee Agenda dated November 13, 2025
submitted by Miss Tiner. Public Works
Committee meeting minutes dated November
13, 2025 submitted by Miss Tener. Um,
water water pollution committee meeting
agenda dated November 14th, 2025
submitted by Mr. Wing. And finally,
finance committee meeting agenda dated
November 17, 2025, submitted by Mr.
Skunover.
>> Mr. President, I make a motion to uh
accept the reports of standing
committees.
>> Second.
>> Uh we have a motion and a second to
accept the reports of standing
committees.
>> Yep.
What just happened? All those in favor
signify say by I was moving on to the
next one. Signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Motion carries. What?
>> Yeah, it's like the staples all that.
All right, I'm going back to the first
page. Please hold.
Okay.
Any reports of special committees?
>> There are no reports this evening.
>> Great. Can even help me stall.
All right,
moving on.
>> Public hearings. We have two of those
this evening. Uh the f
first one on short-term rentals um
instructions for public hearing since
I've skipped half of the previous
instructions where Mr. James didn't know
his three minutes timing. Same
threeminut rule applies. So we're going
to ask for proponents of the legislation
and then we'll give time to opponents in
order to speak the second round of
proponents. If you want a rebutt um any
rebuttal, you're going to have to speak
in the first round. So, any proponents
here to speak on the short-term rental
legislation? Now is the time to do that.
>> Seeing none, I'll ask for opponents to
the changes to chapter 1131 and the
short-term rental legislation in front
of city council.
Seeing none, that means we have a bunch
of people here for the second one. Okay.
All right. So, we're going to move on
from the first public hearing.
Great. We're going to close that public
hearing on short-term rentals to make it
official. Okay. Moving on. We're going
to open the public hearing on the Arbor
Homes Rainbow Drive
zoning map
change.
Is there any preamble for that that I
need to you want to introduce that?
>> Um yeah, I'll just say briefly a couple
folks asked um in the intermission
there. So, this property was reszoned a
while back. I apologize. I can't
remember when, but it's been a while.
and it was put in as a PUD which is a
planned unit development and that's an
overlay on the zoning and there was no
underlying zoning established and so the
zoning map amendment that's before you
tonight is to establish that underlying
zoning and it's for RMD which is read
residential medium density sorry um and
so that's just to establish the size of
lots um and then all of the setbacks and
other things that go with building um on
that parcel
I'm sorry it did go before planning
commission and planning commission did
approve um RMD as the underlying um
zoning for that property for Arbor Homes
to build on.
>> Was it currently zoned?
>> It doesn't have zoning. That's the
point. It has the PUD overlay, but it
doesn't have the underlying zoning.
Yeah. And that's what this establishes.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. So,
same rules as the previous. We're going
to ask for proponents of this
legislation to come up first. Uh if
there are any proponents to the zoning
map amendment, please come forward. And
we're going to there's a clipboard there
for you to sign in, but you're going to
state your name and address for the
record. And then you have three minutes
uh to make your statements.
Hey, good evening. Uh, my name is Drew
Miller. My address is 6797 North High
Street, Warthingington, Ohio. Um, I'm
with Arbor Homes. I am the land
entitlement and zoning manager. Um, we
work in an office in Worthington.
There's uh about 15 or 20 of us in in
that Columbus office and uh we
established that office about four years
ago. Uh Harbor Homes is a very
experienced home builder. We've been
around since 1994. We started in
Indianapolis. Um since then we've built
about 22,000 homes um in Indianapolis um
and a little bit in Louisville, the
Cincinnati Dayton area, and then here in
central Ohio. Um we're really excited
about the potential to bring uh our
houses to Lancaster. We feel like this
is an appropriate location. Um I do have
my engineer here tonight, although this
is just a zoning hearing. So, um I
wasn't going to get too much into that,
but we're happy to answer any questions
everyone might have. We do have a
conceptual plan that we put together,
which we did share at the planning
commission. Um I'm not sure if you all
have seen that yet given this is just
the zoning. I'm not sure, but u we have
started some preliminary engineering on
the site and we we've also completed a
traffic impact study. We are waiting on
comments back from the city for the
traffic impact study, but um we we will
be um adhering to any recommendations
they make, which we do anticipate would
be a deceleration lane and a left turn
lane off of Thornville Road. So, um with
that being said, we did hear quite a bit
of comments at the planning commission
meeting regarding what the site uh what
the neighborhood is going to look and
feel like. And so, um like I said, we do
have that concept plan. We're putting
together a screening exhibit um to share
with folks if the zoning is approved and
we move forward to planning commission.
Um we'd love to share some of those uh
plans with you all. But uh you know we
we are sensitive fact that there is
adjacent neighbors that have been living
there for quite a while. Um, we have
already built into our concept plan a
buffering space uh between the two
neighborhoods and uh we we plan on
putting in some screening. Whether
that's physical or landscaping, we're
open to either of those, but like I
said, we are uh willing to discuss those
if the zoning is approved and and this
moves forward. We're happy to talk about
what that might look like. So, okay.
>> Um that's all I really have, but if you
got any questions for us, I'm happy to
answer.
Um, does council have any questions?
Since he is up here, we will
yield time to you guys for any
questions.
>> All right. Thank you very much.
>> Thank you.
>> There any other proponents of the
project? This is your time to speak. And
keep in mind, if you are a proponent,
don't speak at this time. You will not
be able to speak later.
Seeing none, we'll move on to opponents
of this proposed zoning map change. So,
any opponents opposed to the change,
you're going to want to approach the
podium. You're going to sign in on the
clipboard uh with your name and address.
State the same for the record. And then
>> you'll have three minutes to address
counsel.
>> I have some questions, too. So, it might
take a little more than three minutes.
>> You'll have three minutes to address
counsel. And then if you have questions,
that's
>> Wait a minute. No,
>> that's something that we don't do during
the public hearing.
>> I cannot ask a question.
>> You can ask your questions. You're
they're not going to be answered at this
time. But we will make sure that you get
questions answered from whether it's us
or the
>> first of all, I want to compliment you
for if my three minutes are gone now.
>> No, I haven't started. I was trying to
explain to you. I'm as fair as I can be.
>> Okay. Right.
>> I want to thank you. You have been very
diligent about keeping us up informed
when these meetings are. I compliment
you for that. I'd like to ask a
question. What is the purpose of zoning?
What is the purpose of zoning?
I will get no answer. Uh to me the
purpose of zoning is to protect your
community, to protect your
neighborhoods, to protect an atomic
energy plant from showing up in your
backyard
or to protect a slum from ending up in
your backyard.
Zoning is to help you. This I don't know
if in fact, can I hand this out?
>> Yeah, you pass it around.
>> I know you've seen it.
This is what's being proposed.
There's 19 families around this field.
19. You're putting in 190
in less than 1/5 of a square mile.
You're going to go from 19 families to
219 families.
That's extreme. That's not adding to my
neighborhood. That's invading my
neighborhood.
the I everyone I've showed this map to
their first reaction is oh my gosh
one question to the developer where's
the green space
every development I see in Columbus I go
into I work with schools and I'm in all
the neighborhoods up and down southeast
Ohio and Columbus I'm into the
elementary schools and I see the
neighborhoods and this map has nothing
but straight streets and every
neighborhood hood I've seen built in the
last 50 years has curved streets to help
the traffic. Where are the kids going to
play?
There's nothing in that that has any
space for the kids to do anything except
play in the street.
You developed a straight dragway.
Now, that map is extreme. And let's
consider this. You all play football or
no football? the property sizes on this
on this map.
And by the way, there's some uh
discrepancies.
Uh you're I asked for a definition of
this PCU and they were nice enough and
gave me a good definition
and it's u to promote the redevelopment
of one unit residential dwellings on
moderatesized lots. Well, first of all,
there's no such thing as a small lot.
Moderate is small. And here's how small
this lot is.
Your yard is from the goal line to the
13 yard line
to the middle of the field. I was a
marching band director. I know my
dimensions.
So your goal your your front yard will
be from the goal line to 13 if you do a
40 foot lot, which is what their plan
says in the in the map. If you look at
the map, it says that these lots are
40,000 square feet. 45 40 foot frontage.
>> Sir,
>> your pardon me.
>> I I didn't catch your name when did you
state your name at the beginning?
>> Yes. My name is Robert Lust.
>> And Mr. Lust, your three minutes is up
and I know that you have plenty of other
questions, comments, and concerns and
we'll be happy to address those at
another time. But as the public hearing
goes, your three minutes are up and then
once we go back to proponents and
opponents, then you'll have the ability
to come up and speak for another three
minutes. I'd like to read one definition
that you gave me. This is your
definition.
>> This is not my definition, but this is
my
>> definition. The planning city can give
this definition.
>> This is my meeting. So just you can you
can give the definition in your next
three minutes after opponents
>> to allow
>> are allowed at the sir
>> and and to allow for minimal
non-residential uses such as parks and
schools that are compatible with
>> and maintain the over res the over all
residential character in the area. There
any other opponents that want to speak?
Have any other opponents? Ma'am,
again, you just need to sign on the
clipboard, state your name and address
for the record,
and then you have three minutes to
speak.
Good evening. My name is Linda
McCormack. My address is 2035 Lancaster
Thornville Road,
which is right on the corner of Rainbow
and 188.
I'm very concerned because in the 33
years we've lived there, there have been
several accidents at that T
intersection.
to add an additional
170 homes I believe to 200 to that
intersection is
I don't think it's safe with the
addition of all the uh and I know they
said they did a traffic study that will
be interesting to see because recently
when the city school system moved their
bus garage up on Path Road that
increased the traffic in that area
tremendously. So, and then we do have
two schools right down the road. So,
traffic concern is
one of my biggest concerns. The other
concern is I don't I mean no disrespect
cramming
170 homes into that area. I did have a
couple questions which maybe they could
be answered later, but I would like to
know the process of this whole, you
know, zoning thing like if it if it gets
approved tonight, then what would be the
next steps to move forward and maybe an
approximate time frame for that? Um,
the other question I had was, um, if
this is going to be zoned medium
density, I think that's right, for 40
foot wide lots, what is the next step up
so that if this is going to happen, if
there's going to be a development back
there,
what would be the next step up so that
it's not so crowded and maybe that could
be looked at?
Um, I mean, I understand the city wants
to grow. It's a great location.
Again, we've lived there for 33 years
and we've loved it. But what would be
the next step up? If anyone has that
answer now, I'd love to hear it. If not,
maybe they could get back with me. But
again, I uh wish to express my
opposition to this.
>> Thank you very much.
We have any other opponents that wish to
speak?
Ma'am, if you'd like, you could give
your three minutes and then you can just
state your name and then you can sign in
if you haven't already.
>> Okay. Um, my name is Pam Harris. My
address is not Lancaster Thorn Bill
Road. It was years ago. Mine is 1863
Northshshire Drive. Um, I was not going
to actually speak. I came on behalf of
my parents. If it tells you anything, I
My parents are Linda's neighbor, so
their house backs up to the field. They
built it when I was six months old. I am
57, so that tells you how long they have
resided there. Um, to be completely
honest, I did not go to the first
meeting. Um, they forgot to tell me that
they got the letter. So, I am at this
meeting to represent them. Um, my
biggest concern I think along with Linda
and the traffic around that area because
there are a lot of accidents and when
you sit on their front porch, the
traffic coming down 188 is at a high
rate of speed and you add way more cars
to Rainbow and 188, it's just going to
make it worse. Um, my biggest fear I
think because my mother is in her 90s
and my dad is almost 90 is any kind of
crime that that will bring out there for
them. Um, I know that they get nervous
just at their age being out there and
then you're going to build all these
homes with a bunch of other people and
I'm not sure what caliber of people that
will bring in. So, that's my two cents.
That's why I'm opposed to it. Just
mainly on behalf of my parents.
>> All right. Thank you very much.
>> Do we have any additional opponents that
would like to speak?
All right, seeing none, we're going to
swing back around. This is the
opportunity for proponents, which was
the developer, to come up and speak for
an additional three minutes. Hopefully,
you have the gist of
what everyone's concerned about, and
might be able to answer some questions.
>> Yeah, thank you. Is this on? Oh. Uh so
yeah, we those are a lot of the same
comments that we heard at planning
commission. Um and they're comments that
we take very seriously as a um home
builder. Um they're they're not uncommon
to any city um where we'd be building.
Uh so that is a concept plan at this
point. Um the way that Arbor Homes
operates is um we try to be o open and
transparent as possible. So, we're happy
to, you know, take these comments back
and do what we can with this plan. Um,
as far as the density, open space, lot
sizes go, yes. Um, it it does feel
tight. Um, it it definitely looks tight
when you look at a concept plan like
that. Um, we're very uh proud to to help
first-time home buyers and and help
people attain homes. Um, that's really
important to something to Arbor. Um,
especially just in the the climate here.
um recently, you know, home prices are
just skyrocketing. And so the best way
to achieve uh a more attainable home is
uh you know, is to get them a little bit
denser um and and to get more lots
because that offsets a lot of the hard
costs that we have as a developer um
when we're, you know, creating this
neighborhood. Um as far as traffic goes,
I I did mention that we do have a
traffic impact study. We're waiting
comments back from the city. Um, we do
anticipate, you know, that we will be
able to mitigate any addition additional
traffic that we're putting onto the
roads. Um, there's there's going to be
two access points for this neighborhood,
um, both off Rainbow Drive and Lancaster
Thornville Road. Um, and like I'd
mentioned, right now, we do think that
there will be a de acceleration lane
added and a left turn lane added. So,
um, we feel strongly that we'll be able
to mitigate any traffic concerns, but at
the end of the day, um, it does, you
know, depend on the city and if they
tell us that absolutely there's no way
you can do this, uh, because it's going
to be a traffic issue, um, then, you
know, that's something we're will
willing to understand and walk away
from, uh, but we do leave it, you know,
to the engineers and the professionals
to tell us what needs to be done so that
the roads can accommodate this many
houses. Um, like I said, I I am
sensitive to the fact that a lot of
homeowners have lived in this area for
quite a long time. Um, it's not our goal
to put, you know, neighbors backed up
directly to your property. Um, we're
very interested in putting in, you know,
screening, whether that's landscaping,
mounding, uh, if we have the space for
it, or, you know, even a privacy fence
along that entire side, uh, or where
anybody is. But, you know, those are
those are certainly things that don't
affect the zoning. Those are things we
need to discuss um as we move to the
next stage in the process. Um so yeah,
like I said, I'm happy to, you know,
continue to work on this concept plan.
We will um we'd submit it to the city
and and you know, change some things on
that concept plan based on what we've
heard at planning commission, what we've
heard tonight. Um that is if if you all
approve the zoning, we can move forward
with, you know, making some of those
changes. But we do feel that this is an
appropriate area. it's it's already
located in the city and um you know if
if you look at the neighboring uh zoning
districts this is consistent with um the
zoning that surrounds this property.
>> All right, thank you. Your three minutes
are up. Do you stay there for one
second? Any council members have any
questions?
This Tener,
>> so you talked about the screening and
that have you ever done anything in a
project you said you were going to do
and then you guys didn't do it after you
said you were going to.
>> No, ma'am. Um, we're very proud of the
work we do and I'm man of my word and
you know, I can put that on the record
that um, you know, however we move
forward with a concept plan. We're
already looking at ways that we can
screen um, and provide more privacy for
the existing homeowners. It's definitely
something we're interested in doing. We
don't, you know, we want to be good
neighbors, you know, to everybody. And
um kind of in the spirit of the opening
statement um you know we want to be good
neighbors too. We want to you know
provide a good neighborhood that people
are going to be proud to live in.
>> Well I understand um these individuals
concerns and there is a lot of traffic
on 188. There is. And when I was told
about this actually it was probably
about a month or so ago and somebody
called me from Rainbow Drive and I'm
thinking why are they upset about
Sheridan Drive and here it was Rainbow
Drive. So, I didn't even know about
this. That's another problem I have. I
don't remember knowing about this. So,
um I I'm kind of concerned about I'm
kind of I've seen the map. I'm kind of
concerned about the retention ponds. I'm
just kind of concerned about It is a
lot. That's a That's a lot of houses in
that spot for residences. And I just
don't know how you're going to screen
that from the people. I just don't.
>> Yeah. So, you know, we have ways of
doing it. We we do screening and
landscape screening all the time in our
neighborhoods. Um you know, we just we
need to understand if the zoning is
appropriate. If you all feel like houses
are an appropriate use on this property,
that's going to allow us to spend some
more money to start getting into more
plans that we can share with you all for
feedback. So, you know, I'm hope hoping
that's something that we can do so we
can get that concrete feedback.
>> Mr. Luxembourg.
>> So 40 foot wide lot with a 5ft 5 foot
setback on both sides leaves a 30 foot
wide house.
>> That's correct.
>> Two cars or one car?
>> Two car garage.
>> So that leaves about 8 foot for the rest
of the frontage of the house which will
not meet our zoning code. Was that
raised in planning commission?
>> Uh no. We didn't get too much into those
details since this is just a matter of
zoning at this point. Your garage door
can't be more than a certain percentage
of the frontage of the home.
>> Okay. Yeah.
>> For our zoning code. So, you may need to
look at widening your lots to 50 foot.
Okay.
>> I think just to make it work with our
zoning or you're going to have to get a
variance.
>> Okay. Thank you. Yeah, we'll definitely
look into that.
>> All right. So, any other question? And
just as a reminder, and I'll I'll get to
you in just a sec.
>> Okay. So, as a reminder, the public
hearing is for the zoning change. As far
as what the lots look like, the size,
the density, all of that. Your other
questions that
is not relevant per se to the amendment
of the zoning map, right?
law director.
>> So, the residential medium density, like
I said before, does set what the the lot
width and the setbacks and all of that
are. So, by by making this residential
medium density, you are authorizing the
the minimums that are in the code that
are in the langster codified ordinance.
>> Right. But we're not approving
>> You're not approving that. No,
absolutely.
>> That's Sorry, that's the point I was
trying to make. We're not approving
>> this at all.
>> No. And even if you do approve the
zoning, it's going to go back to
planning commission because they're
going to have to come up with a, like he
said, some kind of concrete plan and
concrete design um that the planning
commission can look at and sign off on.
>> Okay. Thank you, Mr. Als.
>> You stole my thunder. I'm sorry. Go
ahead.
>> Sorry.
>> We're good.
>> Sorry about that.
>> Any other questions from council?
Miss Hoop.
Um, this may be a silly question, but
um, the land owners,
do they, and this might be for Stephanie
Hall, do they approve of these changes
or is it the developer that is allowed
to request them?
>> I'm assuming you have a contract with
the land owner.
>> Yes, we are under contract to purchase
the property. They uh the property owner
did sign our applications for the
reszone.
>> Okay. So then that allows you to y
>> request it. Okay. That's all.
>> Okay. Any other questions?
>> One. Yeah. I'm cur curious why
>> how this property is currently not
zoned. It was just just missed
previously with the last project that
somebody looked at
>> doing. So in part this is really a
cleanup.
>> Yes. essentially
>> of zoning more than saying, "Hey, we're
gonna approve anyone."
>> Yeah, this has been in this city for
quite some time. I apologize. I can't
remember. Do you guys remember from
planning?
>> Yeah, I was gonna say like 30 30 years
plus.
>> Okay.
>> So, yeah.
>> So, I mean, it was necessary to to do
something here because we're cleaning it
up.
>> Yes. Tech.
>> Okay. The zoning rather.
>> All right.
Thank you very much.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay. So, now we're back to opponent
testimony. Whoever spoke the first round
has the ability to come up and speak
again for another three minutes. So, Mr.
Lust, if you want to come up and start
where you left off, you can have another
three minutes to to maybe throw some
additional questions out there.
>> Yes.
The point I was trying to make
was I'm going by your definition when
the first came up and they said this is
going to go to a um whatever the new
zoning thing it was. We looked it up and
when I came into the first planning
commission I read that definition and I
was told oh that's not the definition.
We have our own definition.
So that's what I'm working off is your
definition of what this is. And um
first thing is your definition has some
some discrepancies with theirs. Uh
they're saying 4,000 square lots. Your
definition says minimum lot size 5,000.
And um minimum footage 50.
Yes. So what's on that drawing doesn't
even match what your zoning is. Now,
what I find really uh uh objectional,
and I don't know if I made the point the
first time, there's 19 properties around
this field, which is8
of a square mile. I measured it. It's8
of a square mile. We're going from 19
families to 209. There's 190 properties
on that drawing.
Not only that, please consider this. The
traffic is a very big issue. Are there
there's two other fields in that area
also being developed.
One's already a done deal. I understand.
The one just north of um uh Shortstop
and Tiki Lane going up toward Thomas
Euing. That field in there is all being
developed with several hundred homes,
another 300. And the field across from
the orchard on 188 is being developed.
So we're not talking about our 200 homes
in our field. You're talking about 750
homes in that neighborhood. Now, you got
to consider traffic because guess what?
All that filters down to the hospital
corner.
There's hardly anywhere out. You go
north, you're going out of town. If
you're going into town, you're going in
through the hospital corner, whether
it's on Sheridan or it's on 188
Pleasantville Road. That's a ton of
traffic. Have you ever been around that
hospital corner? I think I've said my
three minutes. Thank you. I do
appreciate it.
>> Thank you. Any
other opponents that spoke the first
round want to come up and speak again?
Miss McCormick.
So, I did have a couple more questions
and I'm hoping that they can get
answered. The one question about the
deceleration.
Did I say that right? The slowdown lane,
which I'm assuming would be southbound
on 188, that I'm assuming will cut into
my corner. Is that what you're
Is that like the proposed plan right
now? Southbound on 188.
>> Ma'am, he's not going to be able to
answer your questions. You just have to
address us.
>> Okay. Do you guys know
>> does anyone know how they will do the
the deceleration lane?
>> Just let me say briefly. Sure. So
there's state of Ohio rightway because
it is a state route and that's that's a
portion in the front of your house um
all the way you know across your
frontage
>> and so it looks like
>> you would access that.
>> Yeah. It looks like.16 acres is what's
in that state of Ohio right ofway.
>> Yeah. So, it will cut into basically my
front yard.
>> Well,
>> even though the state owns it.
>> I was gonna say it's the state.
>> I've been mowing it for 30 some years.
So, why aren't they mowing that?
>> Yeah. Good question.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, they don't mow mine either. I I
don't know.
>> Might have to talk to them. They do put
weed killer out by the fire hydrant
though.
>> Um
>> probably send them a bill. I don't know.
>> I could pay back some of this. Yeah. The
second question I had and and it really
is legitimate actually too
and I don't mean this to be sarcastic if
it comes across sarcastic but do our
concerns
will they affect the approval of this as
taxpaying citizens and homeowners.
Are you guys allowed to answer that?
I didn't mean for it to be rhetorical.
Uh, I mean technically no, but if
someone wants to answer and we can make
it quick. I I I think Do you want me to
take that one? It's it's a it's it's
hard to answer. So yeah, I mean we me
personally and I've sat here for a while
and been in a bunch of these public
hearings where it's it's very nobody
shows up or it's very testy. I love to
use the Timbertop property uh when we
had that public hearing as a Miss Tener
was here with me and it was very
um
>> it's probably very heated.
>> It it was I mean I think a pig farm was
thrown out there at one point but I to
to the point it's it's hard because you
have 19 people that are clearly invested
in it, right? And then for us, we try
and represent everybody's concerns. And
then you look at the totality of the
city's needs. Um, and we hear it all the
time. We're running out of we're running
out of space, but we need affordable
homes. We need nice homes. We need, you
know, we we have debates back and forth
on what what should it look like? Should
it be three-story apartment? Should it
be single family homes? And it it's
really it's really hard because we don't
own the property and then and then
you're asking us to tell a property
owner what they can and can't do with
their property. So
to answer your question in short, we
think about that. It really can be
agonizing. You can lose sleep over it.
Um
at the end of the day, it's what's best
overall for for the city. um and it's
citizens and we try and and think of it
that way.
>> So that's that's the best I can tell
you. I appreciate that.
>> But I right passing this tonight doesn't
mean this whole thing's a done deal
anyway. This is just a
>> format to do one step.
>> This does not mean this is going to
happen. I just But still I know it's a
fear. I got it. It is.
>> Yeah.
>> Nail in the coffin. Nail in the coffin
is not tonight.
>> No, I understand that. I understand
that. Do I have any more time left?
>> Well, I took half your time, so I'll
give you a little more. Go ahead.
>> And I appreciate that. So, is there
again my question is, is there another
level up? But Steve, you already
addressed that according to zoning,
they're not already, you know, the plan
right now does not comply with that. So,
that's somewhat of a comfort. But would
that change the medium density zoning
there? Is there another zoning that
would
This goes back to planning commission a
like if it's zoned, right? I'll let the
law director give you the
>> Okay. So, just to answer a few
questions. Um, you were asking if there
is another less dense level up and there
is. We have what's called residential
low density and that's a 70 foot lot
frontage. Um, as Mr. Lust stated, the
RMD is technically a 50 foot frontage.
Um, it's my understanding that the
developer has proposed 40 feet. I wasn't
at the planning commission. Um, so I I
apologize. I don't know for sure, but
they would have to come back to planning
commission and get a special exception
to um or an area variance actually to
build anything um that was not in
compliance with the current code. Um
>> what was the 70 foot one
>> uh res residential low density
>> low density. Okay. And so that's a
possibility that it could be zoned.
>> So that's a 70 foot lot. Um, we don't
have a whole lot of builders in
Lancaster right now. We haven't had a
lot of interest in anything above a
50-foot lot for a long time. I,
everybody knows, we've built apartments.
We've built lots and lots of apartments.
You know, between the administration and
the economic development director
working together, we've got lots of
apartments, but when it comes to single
family homes, 50 feet is what we're
seeing right now. And that's the only
interest that we're seeing.
>> Okay.
>> Yep.
And then the only other comment I would
like to make, there's been a lot of
discussion about the traffic on 188,
which is what my house faces. Nothing's
been talked about the road situation of
Rainbow itself. If no one's ever been on
Rainbow, it has a lot of hills and
valleys. And if people do not abide by
the speed limit, they can easily not see
anybody that's oncoming
um on the other side of the whoops other
side of the hill. And I don't think the
road is that wide as it is. So I think
that really needs to be taken into
consideration as well. Rainbow is not um
you know there's no room for sidewalks
um and it's not a very wide road. I'm
sure it abides by code, but for that
amount of traffic on Rainbow with Hills
and Valleys. Thank you.
>> Right. Thank you.
Uh, Miss Harris, you're the only
opponent left. So,
>> I feel like I have to say,
>> you're fine. You have another three
minutes if you need them.
>> Um, so, like I said, my parents are
beside Linda. What I think that means
from what they're explaining where they
will put that is my parents own the lot
where their home sits on. They also own
two other lots clear up to the point. So
if I'm understanding correctly, probably
one of the entrances will be at the
point of their lot. Um and then of
course they're almost on the corner of
Rainbow 188. So, they will be completely
surrounded um you know, boxed in by this
development. I hear the gentleman talk
about putting up a wall of sorts. I'm
not going to lie, it shatters my heart
in pieces because my father
still weed whacks and ms all of that. It
will just create more work for him. I
know that that is not a deciding factor.
I do know that this is their homestead
that they built um years ago. It's the
home I was raised in. Um,
they love it there. They are elderly and
I'm just not going to lie, it really
worries me for their safety. It worries
me for them getting out of their
driveway on 188 because it is extremely
busy. Like to sit on their front porch,
you cannot even hear each other talk.
The traffic is literally going 70 miles
an hour in front of their house now. And
so I agree with the other gentlemen like
when you it is I don't want to say a
small neighborhood because they are kind
of separated from each other a little
bit but just the amount of how fast the
cars go down that road right now and
then you're going to potentially add all
of these other cars and all of these
people. I just feel like it puts my
parents who are elderly and who have
lived there all these years at a risk.
So, not that that changes anything, but
I do want to share on behalf of my
parents because they would not speak um
if they needed to, but I know how they
feel about it because they tell me. So,
thank you so much for listening.
>> Okay, so we've gone through our list of
opponents. Proponents have gone twice.
So, that is it.
>> Technically, you're supposed to wrap
with proponents. The proponent speaks,
then an opponent, and then proponents.
You gave an extra opponent, so now you
got to give one more proponent. I
apologize.
>> I gave an extra.
>> Yep. It should be proponent, opponent,
proponent. The end. Yep. But that's
fine. You you're you're accommodating.
>> Drew, you want to come up and
>> give another three minutes?
>> Sorry.
>> Those are the rules. Sorry.
>> Someone didn't write them down for me
and I'm just filling in.
>> U
>> That's me. So earlier there was mention
of a couple other uh neighborhood
developments surrounding surrounding
this area. One of those I I believe was
Power Run uh which I know um fell out of
contract. So I don't think that's going
to be happening right now. But I will
say um our traffic engineers did sync up
with the traffic engineers of those
other neighborhoods. So they're
combining those traffic studies to
understand the really holistic picture
of the traffic situation out there. So
like I said, that is in the city's court
right now. We're waiting for that
feedback. We're going to comply with
whatever they want. If they tell us that
it's a non-starter because traffic is
too much of a problem out there, we'll
walk away. But we're waiting on that
city feedback.
>> Great.
Thank you.
>> Now, I'm good to close. All right. We're
going to unless anyone else has any
comments from council, I'm going to go
ahead and close this public hearing.
Great. Thank you.
I feel like I need a recess after that.
>> All right. Well, we're not doing a
recess. We're going to move right into
the reading of resolutions. Starting
with the third reading of temporary
resolution 8925.
A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to enter into a contract
not to exceed $500,000 with the app
architecture
for design and construction
administration of the 80 road fire
station project and to declare an
emergency. This is through safety
committee Mr. Bisjack and Miss Ter.
>> Mr. Bisjack.
>> Uh thank you Mr. President. I move that
council pass and gross and enter upon
the written record resolution the
resolution temporarily numbered 89-25.
Second.
>> We have a first and second to pass
temporary resolution 8925. Any
discussion?
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Uh once again,
this legislation uh much like what the
preamble says, allows the service safety
director to enter into a contract not to
exceed $500,000.
Uh once again, another step in this
process here of getting a new uh engine
house 2 built on the west side uh on Ed
Road. So this uh legislation is not an
appropriation. That's all. Thank you,
Mr. President.
>> Thank you. Any other questions?
Please call the role.
>> Mr. Gails,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisch,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Skoonberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sullie,
>> Miss Tiner,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> Temporary resolution 8925 passes 10 to
zero.
We'll move on to second readings of
resolutions beginning with temporary
resolution 9025. A resolution to
authorize then announced certificates
for the community development block
grant fund 2073,
CHIP home program fund 2083 and for the
healthy homes grant 2026
year end 2025 project expenditures. This
is through economic development
committee Mrs. Hoop and Mr. Wing.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> thank you. This is second of three
readings. Second of three readings on
temporary resolution 9025.
Temporary resolution 9125.
>> A resolution to authorize the city of
Lancaster auditor to request an advance
of funds from the Fairfolk County
auditor for the city's app aort
aortionment of tax settlements for 2026.
This is through finance committee, Mr.
Skunover and Mr. Als.
>> It's the second of three readings,
please.
That was weird.
>> That was weird.
>> That was me, right? All right. Temporary
resolution 9225,
>> a resolution to authorize the service
safety director to dispense with
competitive bidding due to a sole source
provider and enter into a contract for
the city's enterprise asset and work
management software and to declare an
emergency. This is through
administrative services committee, Mr.
Luenberg and Mr. Bisjack.
>> Mr. Lockenberg. Second of three
readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 9225.
>> Temporary resolution 9325.
>> A resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the income tax fund
2016.
This is through finance committee, Mr.
Skunover and Mr. Sully.
>> And that's going to be second of three
readings, please.
Uh temporary resolution 9425,
>> a resolution to increase receipts,
appropriate from the unencumbered
balance and amend the certificate of
other sources and appropriations with
the county auditor in the hotel motel
fund 80055.
This is again through finance committee,
Mr. Skunover and Mr. Als. Uh this will
also be the second of three readings.
Temporary resolution 9525,
>> a resolution to amend aortion
appropriation
budgets and then amend the certificate
of other sources and appropriations with
the county auditor and to declare an
emergency. This is through finance
committee, Mr. Skoover and Mr. Sully.
>> And this one will also be the second of
three readings.
So, we're going to move on to first
readings of new resolutions, starting
with temporary resolution 9625,
>> a resolution to authorize the service
safety director to enter into a contract
with the redandas for general
engineering services. This is through
water water pollution control committee.
Mr. Wing and Miss Tiner.
>> Mr. Wing.
>> Yes. This is the first of two readings.
The first to two readings on temporary
resolution 9625.
Temporary resolution 9725,
>> a resolution to authorize the mayor on
behalf of the city of Lancaster, Ohio to
participate in
aquous film forming foams products
liability litigation against 3M and
DuPont into declare an emergency. This
is through law committee Miss Crates and
Mr. Bisjek.
Mrs. Crates.
>> Yes. Thank you. I would like to make a
motion that council suspend its rules
and wave the second and third reading of
resolution temporarily numbered 97-25.
>> Second. A motion and a second to suspend
the second and third readings. Any
discussion?
>> Yes. Thank you. Um just briefly uh from
the finance committee meeting. We This
is to allow the city to join a
multi-dist litigation um action. The
city has determined um that it does
qualify as a plaintiff and the deadline
to apply for settlement funds is January
1st. Um but because of the length of
time that it's anticipated to take for
the application process, we'd like to
have suspension on that. There are no
fees to the city um other than the
testing that was needed to determine if
we're plaintiffs because the fees come
out of the settlement funds.
>> Great. Any other discussions on the
motion to suspend?
Seeing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bischack, yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kes, yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luxenberg,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner, yes.
>> And Mr. W.
>> Yes.
>> Motion to suspend carries 10 to zero.
Mrs. Crates.
>> Thank you. I'd like to make a motion to
make a motion that council pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
resolution temporarily numbered 97-25.
>> Second.
>> A motion and a second to pass resolution
9725. Any other discussion?
>> Nothing further. Thank you.
>> Any other discussion from councel and
call the role please?
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack, yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sie.
>> Yes.
>> Miss Tiner.
>> Mr. Wink.
>> Yes.
>> Temporary resolution 9725 passes 10 to
zero.
>> Temporary resolution 9825.
>> A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to enter into a contract
with the Renaissance Counseling and
Consultation to provide professional
mental health counseling services to the
city of Lancaster employees and their
dependents and to declare an emergency.
Mr. Administrative Service Committee,
Mr. Luckenberg and Mr. Bishek.
>> Mr. Luckenberg.
>> First of two readings.
>> First of two readings on temporary
resolution 9825.
Temporary resolution 9925. A resolution
to amend community reinvestment area 3
CR A3 as enacted pursuant to permanent
resolution number 71-9
and a previously amended by permanent
resolution 59-23
and to declare an emergency. This is
through economic development committee
Mrs. Hoop and Mrs. Kates.
>> Mrs. Hoop.
>> Um, yes. So, I'd like to make a motion
that council suspend its rules and wave
the second and third reading of
temporary resolution 99-25.
>> Second. Have
>> a motion in a second to suspend the
rules and wave the second and third
readings of 9925.
Discussion.
>> No.
Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisch,
>> Mr. Cart,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kit,
>> Mrs. H.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Luxenberg?
>> Yes. Mr. Skunover.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tiner,
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Motion to suspend passes 10 to zero.
>> Mrs. Hoop.
>> I would like to make a motion that
council pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
99-25.
>> Second.
A motion and a second to pass
engross on upon written
9925. Any discussion?
>> Um, no. This is we talked about this in
finance. It's just to include the
annexed areas into the CRA.
>> Great. Any other questions?
Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bisch, yes.
>> Mr. Carr, yes.
>> Mrs. Kes,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. H. Yes.
>> Mr. Luberg.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Scoover?
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Mr. Sully.
>> Yes.
>> Miss Tiner.
>> And Mr. W.
>> Yes.
>> Temporary resolution 9925 passes 10 to
zero.
>> Temporary resolution 100-25.
>> A resolution to authorize the service
safety director and the city engineer to
apply for the transportation
alternatives program grant through the
Ohio Department of Transportation for
the Memorial Piers pedestrian
improvement project and to declare an
emergency. This is through public works
committee. Miss Tiner and Mr.
Lumpenberg.
>> Miss Tiner.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council suspend it rules and wave
the second and third readings of
temporary resolution 100-25.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion, a second to suspend the
second and third readings on temporary
resolution 125. Any discussion, Miss
Tiner?
>> Not this time.
>> Any other discussion on the motion to
suspend?
Please call the role.
>> Mr. Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kit,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> Motion to suspend passes 10 to zero.
Miss Tiner.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council passing gross and enter
upon the written record temporary
resolution 100-25.
>> Second. We have a motion and a second to
pass temporary temporary resolution 125.
Any discussion?
>> Yes, this is a applied for a grant for
the pedestrian memorial pedestrian area.
Uh it's a construction grant and it
would if awarded uh we it would be an
8020 match. We play pay the 20% but we
have to have it applied for by the 30th
of November.
Any other discussion on the motion to
pass? Seeing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bishack, yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lotober,
>> Mr. Scrunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sy,
>> Miss Ter, yes. And Mr. W.
>> Yes.
>> Motion carries 10 to zero.
That is the end of
resolutions this evening. We are going
to move on to
ordinances.
Um
I'll wait till we
>> Okay.
>> All right.
Uh temporary ordinance 5725
>> an ordinance to establish the
compensation for the city treasurer for
the term commencing payroll 1 2026 and
to declare an emergency is through
finance committee Mr. Skenover and Mr.
trails.
>> That is me and I'm going to make a
motion that we table
temporary ordinance 5725.
>> Second.
>> That is non-debatable. So, we will call
the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisch,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kates,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Scooter,
>> yes.
>> Um, yeah, I'm sorry. Yes. Mr. Sie.
>> Yes.
>> Miss Tiner.
>> And Mr. May.
>> Yes.
>> All right. Motion to table passes 10 to
zero.
Temporary ordinance 5825.
An ordinance to adopt and enact the city
of Lancaster cyber security program
pursuant to the Ohio Revised Code
Chapter 9 miscellaneous section 9.64 64
political subdivision cyber security
this is through law committee Mrs. Kates
and Mr. Bjac
>> Mrs. crates.
>> Yes. Thank you. I would like to make a
motion that council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record ordinance
temporarily numbered 58-25.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion in a second to pass
temporary ordinance 5825. Any
discussion?
>> Uh just briefly, this legislation helps
the city maintain compliance with a new
requirement passed by the state
requiring a cyber security program by
January 1st, 2026. Um our IT department
has drafted that up. And just as a note,
um the cyber security program and
related related records are not
considered part of Ohio public law.
>> Public records law.
>> Thank you. Any other questions?
>> Seeing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bischack, yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kes, yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Scooter,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Teener, yes.
>> And Mr. Wink,
>> yes.
Temporary ordinance 5825 passes 10 to
zero.
Temporary ordinance 5925.
An ordinance to amend the city of
Lancaster's zoning map to change the
zoning of 356
plus or minus acres identified as
Fairfield County auditor tax parcel
number 0534162500
from planned unit development district
to residential medium density district.
This is through code enforcement and
zoning committee Mr. Sully and Mrs.
Hoop.
>> Mr. Sully.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and engross and enter
upon the written record ordinance
temporarily numbered 5925.
>> I second.
>> Was that a second? I'm sorry.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Uh we have a motion and second to
pass temporary ordinance 5925.
Discussion.
>> Uh just want to make real clear, I know
we covered this uh multiple times
earlier, but tonight we are just this is
just for zoning. This is actually this
legislation in my opinion is is cleaning
up something that was missed previously.
By no means are we approving uh a plat a
final plat. And there's a lot of steps
that are still going to have to be that
a developer is going to have to go
through. So I just want to make sure
everybody understands that's what we're
voting on here tonight.
>> Any other discussion?
Seeing none, please call a role.
>> Mr. Ess.
>> No.
>> Mr. Bisjack.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> no.
>> Mrs. Kitz,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Lockchnberg,
>> no.
>> Mr. Skunberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner,
>> no.
>> And Mr. Wing?
>> Yes.
You're have to math that one out for me.
>> All right. Motion to pass temporary
ordinance 5925 passes 6 to 4.
Temporary ordinance 6025.
>> A an ordinance to amend the Lancaster
codified ordinance part 11 planning and
zoning title three zoning and property
restrictions. and to adopt chapter 113
short-term rentals code enforcement.
This is through code enforcement and
zoning committee. Mr. Sully and Mr.
Luenberg.
>> Mr. Sully.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and engross and enter
upon the written record ordinance
temporarily numbered 6025.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion and second to pass
temporary ordinance 6025. Discussion.
>> Not at this time. No. Any other
discussion on 6025?
Seeing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bischack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kites,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lenberg,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> Uh, motion to pass temporary ordinance
does pass 10 to zero. temporary
ordinance.
Hold on a second.
Benefit. We're going to go through 65.
>> 66.
>> The last one.
>> Yep.
>> All right. All right, I'm going to have
the clerk read the preamble to temporary
ordinance 6125
through 6625. Those are all of the
pay ordinances that we discussed before.
And then we'll make a motion to tables.
So,
>> real quickly, can I ask a question?
>> Yeah.
>> I thought you were going to do a motion
to replace temporary ordinance 6225 with
6225 star and then put it on the table
so that it was already done. Is was that
the
>> Yeah, you're right.
>> Okay. Okay.
>> Just wanted to make sure. Thank you.
>> Well, let's do
>> what is
>> Can we skip 62 in that bunch or do you
>> If somebody makes a motion to go out of
order then and everybody approves it
then yes.
>> I move that we go out of order. Mr.
President,
>> I'll second.
>> Second.
>> Just yay and naz.
>> All in favor say I.
>> Yeah. All in favor say.
>> All oppose. Same sign. You can come over
here and sit. You making it difficult
and Oh, are you taking me to dinner this
evening?
>> All right. Okay. So, now we're out of
the regular order of business and we can
read temporary ordinance 6225.
an ordinance to establish benefits,
titles, and compensation for those
employees who are not members of the
recognized bargaining units employed by
the city of Lancaster, Ohio for the year
2026 and to declare an emergency. This
is through finance committee u Mr.
Scoover and Mr. Als.
>> All right. I would like to make a motion
that we replace
6225 with 6225 star as given to the
clerk before tonight's meeting.
>> Second.
>> Thank you. We have a first and a second.
Any discussion?
That one we had a couple meetings ago,
right? or we changed a couple pieces on
one of the position steps, right?
>> Yes.
>> Sorry.
>> Yeah, we had the utilities position that
we needed to remove because I missed
that one and then we had one other range
that we that we adjusted in the
municipal gas.
>> Perfect. Thank you.
All right. Any other discussion?
Seeing none, I will
Ask to call call the role please.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Christ,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luenberg,
>> Mr. Skover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Ter,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wick,
>> Motion to replace carries 10 to zero.
Okay.
Now the clerk will read 6125
through 6625.
>> Okay.
>> And you can take a break in between.
>> 6125. An ordinance to establish the
benefits, titles, and compensation for
the management and professional person
personnel employed by the city of
Lancaster for for the year 2026 and to
declare an emergency through finance
committee. Mr. Skinner, Mr. ALS
um
ordinance temporary 62-25 star an
ordinance to establish benefits titles
and compensation for those employees who
are not members of the recognized
bargaining units employed by the city of
Lancaster Ohio for the year 2026 and to
declare an emergency again through
finance committee Mr. Skover Mr. ALS
Ordinance Temporary 63-25, an ordinance
to establish the benefits, titles, and
compensation for seasonal interns to be
employed by the city of Lancaster during
the summer of 2026 and to declare an
emergency. This is through finance
committee, Mr. Skoover and Mr. Sully.
Ordinance temporary 64-25,
an ordinance to establish the benefits
and titles and compensation for the
information technology administrator,
office of the clerk of court, employ
this by the city of Lancaster, Ohio,
commencing the first pay period of 2026
and to declare an emergency. This is
through finance committee, Mr. Skinner,
Mr. Sullie.
Ordinance temporary 65-25, an ordinance
to establish the benefits, titles, and
compensation for the Fairfield County
Municipal Court, management, and
professional personnel employed by the
city of Lancaster, Ohio for year 2026,
and to declare an emergency is through
finance committee, Mr. Skunover, and Mr.
Sully. And finally, an ordinance to
establish benefits, titles, and
compensation for the Fairfield County
Municipal Court judicial and probational
personnel employed by the city of
Lancaster for the or Ohio for the year
2026 and to declare an emergency. This
through finance committee, Mr. Skinner,
Mr. Sully.
>> Good job.
Uh, I'm going to make a motion that
council place on the table temporary
ordinances 6125
through 6625.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second. Any other
discussion? Again, those are pay
ordinances. We will wait to take up for
passage next meeting after we discuss
the budget.
Notable.
>> It's Yeah, it's non debatable.
>> What am I reading?
>> I don't know. Please call.
>> Yeah. Call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kit,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Scooter,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> God bless you.
>> Motion carries 10 to zero. There you go.
>> Abbit.
>> Temporary ordinance 6725.
An ordinance providing the issuance and
sale of revenue notes in the aggregate
principal amount of 6001,400
$247
to pay cost of improving Ed Road
Memorial Drive and Michael's Way by
grading, widening, paving, curbing and
improving bridges and railroad
crossings, relocating utilities and
installing sidewalks, traffic signals
and signs and water sanitary and storm
water lines and facilities together with
all necessary apartments
there to and declare an emergency. This
through finance committee, Mr. Scooter
and Mr. Als,
>> I'd like to make a motion that council
pass and grow and upon the written
record temporary ordinance 6725.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to
pass.
I don't have any discussion. Anyone else
have any discussion?
Seeing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kates,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Scootermer,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner, yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Motion carries 10 to zero. Temporary
Ordinance 6825,
>> an ordinance providing the issuance and
sale of a revenue note in the aggregate
principal amount of $186,57758
to reimburse Flagstar Bank NA for a draw
on the letter of credit in connection
with cost of improving Ed Road, Memorial
Drive, and Michael's Way by grading,
widening, paving, curving, and improving
bridges and railroad crossings.
Relocating utilities and installing
sidewalks, traffic signals and signs and
water sanitary and storm water lines and
facilities together with all necessary
pertinances there too in declaring an
emergency. This is through finance
committee Mr. Skoover and Mr. Als and
I'd like to make a motion that council
pass and gross and enter upon the
written record temporary ordinance 6825.
>> Second.
A motion and a second to pass. Any
discussion?
Seeing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisher,
>> Mr. Cart,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Craig,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Scooter,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Ter, yes. And Mr. W.
>> Yes.
>> Motion carries 10 to zero.
Moving on to
second reading of ordinances beginning
with temporary ordinance 6925.
>> An ordinance to grant to grant to South
Central Power Company it successors and
assigns a franchise for the right to
acquire, construct, maintain and operate
in the streets their their affairs
alleys.
I hope I said that right. Alley's
bridges and public places of the city of
Lancaster, Ohio lines for the
transmission and distribution of
electric power and energy to the city
and the inhabitants thereof for light,
heat, power, and other purposes and for
the transmission of the same within
through or across said city to and to
declare an emergency. This is through
law committee, Mr. Bisjack and Mr. Mr.
Skinner,
>> Mr. Bjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This will be
the second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
ordinance 6925.
Moving on to first reading of ordinances
with temporary ordinance 7025
>> emergency ordinance creating an
incentive district and declaring
improvements to certain real property
within the incentive district to be a
public purpose and exempt from real
property taxation identifying certain
public infrastructure improvements
that once excuse me that once made will
benefit or serve the parcels in the
incentive district requiring the owners
of those parcels to make service
payments in lie of taxes. Authorizing
the city to require minimum service
payments if such payments are agreed
upon by developer. Establishing an
incentive district public improvement
tax increment equivalent fund for the
deposit of such service payments and as
applicable minimum service payments
authorizing payments to this Lancaster
City School District and approving
related matters. Mr. Economic
Development Committee, Mrs. Hoop and Mr.
Wing.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> this is first of two readings.
First of two readings on temporary
ordinance 7025.
That's the last on my list of
ordinances. Do we have any additional to
become to come before us?
Seeing none, uh we move on to tabled
legislation. As we discussed before,
we're not going to do anything with
those this evening. That's the budget
and one of the other pay ordinances. So,
we'll leave those. Do we have any
unfinish unfinished business?
Seeing none, do we have any new
business?
Mrs. Crates,
>> thank you. Um just briefly, the law
committee um last me last met on
November 7th at which time we reviewed
and discussed some proposed updates to
the council rules which included some
updated language clarifications
um as well as one item that we were
unable to
really move forward on until we had some
guidance from um the greater council.
Um, so the law committee members
discussed concerns over the current
committee structure, specifically the
fact that we have 10 members of council
and only nine committees, which leaves
one member without a committee to chair.
So based upon that, we tried to come up
with additional options and asked the
law director to draft those up so that
we could take a look at those and then
have um, city council kind of give us
some options on guidance on how you
would like to like for the law committee
to move forward. And law director Hall,
is there anything that you would like or
you think I should add to that before
kicking it over for discussion?
>> Um, no. I I'll just say I provided three
handouts. Um, and the first is the uh
standing committee options that the law
committee asked me to draft. Um,
in doing that, the thought was
originally, um, especially on the part
of the administration that we would like
to see fewer committee meetings. Um and
so or I'm sorry option one is more is 10
committees so that everybody has a
committee but the general feeling was at
the meeting that everybody would like to
consolidate it into five meetings. And
so that's what options two and three and
then four and five are. Um at the
meeting it was debated whether it if
there were five committees it should be
a chair co-chair um situation or a chair
excuse me vice chair situation. So
that's why you have two options for each
of those second tables there. Um, and
then I provided the city's org chart
just so that you could kind of think
about whether or not you know these
classifications make sense to you.
Again, this was just me, you know,
spitballing it based on the direction
that I received from law committee. And
then the final uh piece of paper is a
table that has um just I put down 10
members. And then um I looked at what
how many committees each of you would
have to serve on. If there were 10
committees versus how many committees
each of you would have to serve on if
there were five committees. And if there
are 10 committees, then each of you
would serve on three different
committees because we have to have three
people per committee at least. But if
there were five committees, each of you
would serve on six committees uh a
piece. And so just wanted to make it
clear that's why I provided those
handouts.
>> And then just to add because we don't
have a special law committee committee
meeting and we wanted to um have this
before council before the end of the
year. That's why we haven't scheduled
anything additional and we wanted to
talk about it during new business
tonight.
So I wanted to open it up for
discussion. Um as law director Hall said
she has summarized the options that the
committee discussed on that sheet with
the standing committee options.
Just wanted to open it up and see if
anybody had anything they wanted to chat
through.
Any thoughts?
Any thoughts on increasing to 10
committees versus five committees? We
chatted about different options, right?
More council member involvement in
smaller in a smaller structure of
committees helps with that transparency
as well as for administrative attendance
and meetings and public attendance and
meetings as well. But then again, 10
meetings, everyone gets one the chair.
>> Yeah. And I'll I'll add in there, so we
didn't we had 10 committees at one time
and then we shrunk them down, right? Um,
since I've been sitting up here, um,
this term we changed it up. We didn't
want to create an additional committee
because we felt like we consolidated the
last time for good reason because we had
a committee that was basically I think
parks. Um
>> when I first got on I was there was nine
committees and I was on the parks and we
really didn't need a parks per se
committee with council because that was
all it was. So then we put it with
service finally with gas and all that.
That's how that happened. So we made
minor tweaks and went down, you know, to
do that. And then like this term, I
didn't as prom, I didn't have a chair. I
just I was on four different committees.
And then of course it worked out when
Mr. Wolfinger resigned. It just made it
easier for me to to slide into that. Now
we have a different
situation. So that's why the
conversation kind of came up. And I I
mean I don't know. I so we've always
kind of been rotated. It's up to the
prom to decide who, you know, which
council member sits on which committee
and things like that. But and then it's
really up to individual council members
like you're attending the ones that
you're the committees you're assigned
to, but how many you know do you go to
any of the other ones? Do you know
what's going on in the other committee?
So I think that was kind of the
discussion on do we drop it down to
five? Yes, it's less meetings for the
administration, but council members are
I don't want to say forced, but you're
going to be going to more committee
meetings. So, that was kind of I guess
the the idea on that when we were having
that conversation. It does create more
meetings for us, but most of these
committees meet every other month. Um,
so you know, I think were we wanting
action on this or just an open like,
hey, that sounds good. That doesn't
sound good. What are we? It's kind of
awkward because
>> we haven't done this.
>> And we're deciding it for the next term.
So I I don't know.
>> It's not really deciding, right? It is
just giving the law committee guidance
on what the larger or I guess what more
people on council would like to see
before we bring something to council for
you to consider and vote on. I think I'd
also like to add um one of the things
one of the benefits I think personally
of having these smaller committees is
when I first came to council I had no
idea right I had no idea how to run my
committee. I had no idea what I was
supposed to do. And having a chair,
co-chair or a chair um and vice chair
helps those new members with those
senior members bringing them along and
mentoring and helping them understand
the process and what they should be
doing. Um just my two cents.
>> So I just have a question. So like
utilities, public works, you would have
the all these departments together in a
meeting.
Is that what you mean? I mean I I it's
kind of
>> utilities
>> like let's say utilities, public work,
you got gas, utilities, collection,
sanitation, water, all that. Is that
going to be all in one meeting?
>> What what do you
>> that's one of the options
>> because that's I mean there's some that
probably need to not meet as much that
that's why I'm I mean honestly this
other
>> I mean that's up to you guys. I mean,
but I'm just saying cuz there's some
that need to be really meet more than
um like four uh what is it? Some
committees meet what four times a year,
you know, and I mean some of these I
mean there's a lot of work that's done.
>> So
Michael can tell you and Larry can tell
you I mean with the water thing I mean
they're constantly constantly doing
something. It's to keep up on it and to
be updated.
So, I'm just putting that out there.
>> I mean, I would agree the
I think some of them where you have very
little action.
>> I mean, yeah, you try and group them
together as best as you can, but I don't
think it's perfect, but I think that's
as
perfect as it gets. Yeah.
>> Guess we would ask first of all, right,
what's council's appetite for reducing
it or increasing it?
I like, for what it's worth, I I think
that it's been helpful to go to other
committees that you're not chairing
because you do get a feel for how things
work and especially if you're new and we
have a lot of new people on. So,
um, as far as like I'm looking at the
enterprise fund on option four and five
if would they like wouldn't they all
have to come if you met more frequently?
Could you just call certain people? I
don't know if
>> so you're like two departments come this
month and the other two department come
the following certain something like
that.
>> You know, as long as you publish your
agenda.
>> Yeah. If you're the chair, you can
decide.
>> Like I'm thinking the gas department.
you don't have to see as often.
>> I would imagine it's at the pleasure of
the chair of who comes at the end of the
day. Just as you know, once again, the
law director Hall's point, you publish
everything 24 hours in advance,
>> but I like the five.
>> Yeah,
>> I like we're more involved in more,
>> right? So, the chair and the vice chair
could decide, okay, how often are we
meeting? We also can decide what time
>> the the meetings are. So
I personally I like the five because it
it kind of forces the issue of you know
well I've I've said it before in front
of everyone like hey if you're not on a
committee and you're not going to those
other committee meetings you are
>> basically trusting that all the other
council members when they're bringing
legislation they're describing it they
know what they're talking about. So,
which you would hope that that's the
case and then you know if someone
someone doesn't like a particular piece
and you're hoping that it gets to the
floor um in one piece um I think it does
lead to a little more participation. And
I know it makes it hard for some
people's schedules to to make certain
meetings, but then again, that's a
discussion like, hey, when are you going
to schedule them and those things? So,
that's kind of a little further down the
road. But me personally, I like the
shrinking it to five to consolidate it
to to kind of give all of us a little
more
buy in on different committees.
>> If I may say, Mr. President, as well, I
I share that same sentiment. I'm
personally partial to option number
three. Um
I think it's, you know, clear
delineation in terms of chairs and vice
chairs and all that good stuff. So yeah,
but I like the option of a smaller
amount of committees.
>> Any other thoughts?
>> I agree with that as well, Michael.
>> Yeah, I don't mind consolidating. Um I
won't be here next year, so depends what
you guys want to do, I guess. But um I I
would just warn everyone just be careful
of how you handle the water. Like Miss
Tina said there's other always a lot
going on.
>> Did you say economic development meets
four times a year? Is that what you
>> Yeah, we don't meet that often.
>> Well, that's shocking. As much growth is
going on. Economic development only
needs four times a year with with zoning
and with um planning commission and you
know all this going on four times a
year. That's not enough when it happens.
Yeah. I think that's kind of
>> all right. So, that's up to
>> But that's up to you guys. But I'm just
saying
>> chairs later. Well, and then I would say
for the new council members, whether
they're here or they're watching, I
think we need to get I think it'd be
fair to get a little feedback um from
them, which we'll try and make sure that
we reach out before we
definitely bring something forward. I'll
go to you.
>> I can do that or I'll have President
Porter do that. Either way.
>> Um, no, I I can do that. So, there's two
of them sitting here. So,
we can always talk after the meeting or
if it's too late, we can talk later.
>> Three.
>> I didn't even see Amy. She back there.
>> She's hiding. Okay, there you are.
>> Okay. So, yeah, we'll we'll reach out.
We'll kind of figure that out, too. Go
ahead. Just just to put it out there for
council people, if you do this job the
way you're supposed to do it, you take
your phone calls, you do this, it's just
not a well, we're going to come and
we're going to read our legislation the
day before. You need to keep up on
stuff. It's a lot more than what people
think it is. So, I think you guys need
to have meetings. I I just think it's
going to be a cluster because you need
to know what's going on. And you know,
that's part of what you ran for, to have
committee meetings, to be with your
constituents, to to have meetings, even
if it's a one-on-one with
administration. You know, you need to do
your job, and that's all I got to say.
>> Okay, perfect. So,
nothing has been expedited this evening,
I feel like. So, yeah. Thanks. Um, we're
just gonna I'm just gonna go around.
We're not
>> Okay,
>> you can you can take a vote if you want
to, or you don't have to take a vote.
I'm just saying I can't I can't finish
the rules until
>> we're we're just going to So, I'm just
going to ask everyone kind of like if
you had to blurt it out right now, what
Mr. Sully, what's your what's your
option number?
>> Uh, let's see here. That was number
three.
>> Mr. Mack, also option number three.
>> Yeah,
>> three.
>> One,
>> Kind of jamming on three myself.
One
>> one
>> one car
>> being the new guy I would three is where
I'm
>> okay
looking out for my friends at water I'm
going to say five
>> all right miss who
>> I just like the smaller
I I don't know I can't without I'd have
to sit at home look I don't know I have
no opinion but
>> okay
>> I mean I do but not
you're at least not number one
>> no not one but the other two I I don't
know.
>> All right. So, we'll again we'll get
with the others and then we'll have
another discussion and then we'll
>> figure out what to how to bring it
forward.
>> I would have to understand what the role
of a vice chair is because what you're
saying that you have 10 committees, you
have 10 council people that chair
committees.
>> If you have five committees, you have
five chairs and five vice chairs,
>> right?
>> Who wants to be a vice chair?
You know,
>> I like chairing a committee.
>> It's my committee. First thing I did
when I took over the service committee
was ask the people involved in the
service committee,
>> do you want to meet every month? Do you
want to meet? And they said, "No, we
don't. We want to meet once a quarter."
So that's what we did,
>> right? So
it's going to be hard for me to sit and
shut up as vice chair of any committee.
So if it if that is the role
>> well I I think um I can't do it.
>> Yeah. I I think that lends to uh we
won't make you a vice chair.
>> Okay.
>> I mean
>> I don't know.
>> So one person It's like you know when
you you're in a
>> that's not a hill I'm willing to die on.
Larry
>> kind of like when you're in college and
you have a group of four people and one
person does the work for everybody. Kind
of like that.
I'm also the only person on council
that's retired. So, I don't really care.
>> I'll show up where I need to show up
>> when I need to show up and
>> but I feel that if the responsibility of
chairing a committee is
>> a big deal
>> and you should chair.
>> Okay. All right. So, we'll circle back
around to that. Just not right now.
>> So, now we're going to have a lazy.
>> All right. Any additional new business?
Seeing I I wouldn't say that, but um All
right. Uh let's go with the announcement
of scheduled meetings, please.
>> We have December 1st of next of the next
regular scheduled sessions of council
December 1st, 2025 at 6:30 p.m. Castle
Chambers and December 15, 2025 at 6:30
here in council chambers.
>> Thank you. and no special meetings
scheduled. How about regular scheduled
committee meetings, please?
>> I have four of them. I have code
enforcement committee November 20th at
7:30 a.m. City Hall 1897 conference
room. Safety committee um was on
December 5th, correct?
>> Yes. Uh yes. Uh thank you, Mr.
President. Madam Clerk, just want to
confirm for the record after discussing
with committee members in the
administration, safety committee uh on
December 5th is hereby canled. Thank you
everybody for your time.
>> I have service committee December 12th
at 8 a.m. at city hall 1897 conference
room. And then finally water water
pollution committee December 15th at
7:30 a.m. City Hall 1897 conference
room.
>> Uh reading the bills please. I have two
of them for MNCO for $102.70
for publication of ordinances and I have
one for $6821 cents for public notice
for short-term rentals.
>> Mr. President, I make a motion to pay
the bills.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion and a second to pay the
bills. All in favor signify by signify
by saying I.
>> I.
>> Motion carries. No executive session
needed. I would like to accept a motion
that we adjourn.
>> Oh. Oh, I do. I did forget. I have a
liquor license.
>> I have a liquor license for Sweeny's Pub
that was under new business. And I do
apologize.
>> We got sidetracked.
>> So, do I make a motion?
>> Um, or do we
>> move to go out of order and return to
new business?
>> Sure. Sounds good.
>> All right.
>> Man, I feel like
seconds.
>> Okay. is Jack. I do apologize.
>> Yeah. Um I did receive something back
from
Nick Snyder, Chief Snder, and there were
several calls on there. Um but Miss
Paul, do you have anything that you
would like to add on Sweeny's?
>> Oh, okay. Okay. Um so this is a transfer
of ownership um from one entity to
another. Um, typically the Department of
Commerce is supposed to send more
in-depth um, background check
information to the police department. I
don't believe that Chief Snder has
received that yet, or if he has, he
hasn't forwarded it on, and typically
he'll forward it on as soon as he has
it. Um, so I don't know anything about
who is going to take over that um, that
liquor permit. Uh what I will say is
Chief Snyder indicated that he didn't
believe that they had more calls than
your normal bar. Um and that excludes
establishments that sell both food and
alcohol. Um but he did say that there
have been more this year recently than
there have um in years past. So he saw
some kind of trend upward. Um, if you
all would like to wait until the next
meeting to see if we can get that uh
ownership information, the background
information, um, then I absolutely
understand. If you want to go ahead and
and approve it now, that's up to you,
too. It's your choice.
>> This is due 124 of 2025. So,
>> so it just has to be postmarked by 124
>> and you'll meet again on 121.
>> Yes. So, we'll have one more meeting if
you guys want to.
>> I say we wait. I think that's the
prudent thing to do.
>> All right. So you guys want to wait on
taking any action on that?
>> Okay, we will wait until next meeting.
>> Now that motion
>> I move to adjurnn.
>> Make a motion to adjourn.
>> We're using Becky. Sorry. You can second
because unless Larry That's not a hill
I'm dying on either.
>> All right. So all right, we're
adjourned.
>> It's 8:29. Thank you very much and
please sign all your legislation.